Workers Education Bureau of America Records 5277
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Workers Education Bureau of America Records
1920-1954
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Workers Education Bureau of America
5277
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Bibliographies, reports (documents).
Consist of governance and financial documents, reports, correspondence, memoranda and notes pertaining to radio programs, courses and programs to promote workers' education, adult and vocational schools and educational programs (1921-1951).
3834441
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 18, 2003
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 23, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1921 by a group of unionists and educators, the Workers' Education Bureau of America (WEB) functioned under the directorship of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners as a service organization for research, teaching, publication, and extension work in workers' education. WEB received financial, political, and consultative support from American Federation of Labor (A.F. of L.) leaders, including Samuel Gompers, William Green, and Matthew Woll. In 1951, WEB was formally integrated into the A.F. of L. as its Education Department.
Scope and Contents
Section 1. History: Records consist mainly of correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to the routine administration and activities of the Workers' Education Bureau of America. Organizational records include financial statements and auditors' reports (1922- 1947); bibliographies; reading lists; clippings; and certificates of incorportation and certification. Also, memoranda, letters and reports pertaining to the Labor Book Fund; workers' education programs in various states; the Federal Emergency Relief Administration-WEB jointly sponsored West Coast School of Unemployed Workers (1934); the WEB-A.F. of L. dispute with Brookwood Labor School (1929); financial matters; the establishment of a labor correspondence school, the International Labor News Service for Worker Education, the Pittsburgh Labor College, and the A.F. of L. Education Department.
Includes correspondence chiefly of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners with Samuel Gompers and William Green (presidents, A.F. of L.) and Matthew Woll (vice president, A.F. of L.); the American Association of Adult Education; William Haber (professor, Michigan State College); William J. Bowen (president, Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union of America); Victor A. Olander (secretary-treasurer, Illinois State Federation of Labor); and Fannia M. Cohn (secretary, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union) pertaining to the Workers' Education Bureau Press Inc., workers' education, A.F. of L.-WEB relations and joint programs, and leadership training.
Section 2. Organizational activities: Records consist of memoranda, reports, correspondence and miscellaneous documents pertaining to WEB relations with the A.F. of L.; various workers' education programs conducted by unions, academia, and government agencies; and the founding and development of WEB. Include documents pertaining to the establishment of the Labor Book Fund (1922-1928). Also, reports, memoranda and notes pertaining to vocational, adult, and workers' education programs in various states (1935-1939); A.F. of L-WEB joint conferences on labor and public education; Rutgers University-New Jersey Federation of Labor-WEB joint conferences on international labor relations (1946-1947); and Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) workers' education radio broadcasts (1939). Additionally, correspondence of Spencer Miller with Harry Russell (director, WEB, New England Region) on regional conferences and programs (1925-1928); of Sterling Fisher (director of educational radio talks, CBS) on research and radio broadcasts (1939); and of William Green on workers' education programs in academia (1935).
Also, correspondence of John D. Conners with Harold Taylor (president, Sarah Lawrence College) on Fulbright Scholarships, and worker and student exchange programs with Ruskind College, Oxford Univ., and with Matthew Woll on WEB and A.F. of L. cooperative projects and workers' education programs. Also, correspondence of Woll (in the capacity of labor chairman, National Advisory Council on Radio in Education) with William Green and President Franklin D. Roosevelt regarding WEB radio broadcasts (1932).
Section 3. Publications and research documents: Consist of reading lists and bibliographies; published and unpublished pamphlets and reports; notes, memoranda, and manuscript drafts of reports on research projects; and news releases and bulletins of WEB and various cooperating agencies. Include materials by Samuel Gompers, Edward C. Lindeman, Theresa Wolfson, John D. Conners, Mark Starr, Fannia Cohn, Nelson H. Cruikshank, and Arthur Elder pertaining to workers' education; public speaking; child labor; leadership training; collective bargaining; voluntary unionism; the history of the A.F. of L.; labor plays; social security; unemployment; workmen's compensation; labor and the economy; labor history; unions and the community; the construction industry; and the international labor relations programs conducted by the American Council of Education and the American Friends Service Committee.
Section 4. Miscellaneous correspondence and reports: Consist chiefly of published and unpublished reports; routine correspondence of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners; and notes and memoranda. Materials regard workers' education and the atomic age, international labor problems, leadership training, radio programs, technology and unemployment, regional workers' education programs, teacher training, and unemployment (1921-1951).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Adult education teachers -- Training of -- United States; Child labor -- United States; Construction industry -- United States; Educational exchanges -- United States; Press, Labor -- United States; Radio in adult education -- United States; Social security--United States.; Unemployment -- United States; Unemployment, Technological -- United States; Vocational education--United States.; Workers' compensation--United States.; Adult education teachers; Working class -- Education -- United States; Working class -- Drama -- United States; Labor unions -- Officials and employees -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Social activity; Unemployment insurance -- United States; Workers' education -- United States; Workers' education -- United States -- Curricula; Bowen, William J.; Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia Mary), 1885-; Conners, John D.; Cruikshank, Nelson H.; Elder, Arthur H.; Fisher, Sterling; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Green, William, 1872-1952; Lindeman, Eduard; Miller, Spencer, 1891-; Olander, Victor A., 1873-1949; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882- 1945; Russell, Harry A.; Starr, Mark, 1894-; Taylor, Harold, 1947; Wolfson, Theresa, 1897-1972; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; American Association for Adult Education; Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers International Union of America; Brookwood Labor College; Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.; Illinois State Federation of Labor; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; New Jersey State Federation of Labor; Ruskind College (University of Oxford); Rutgers University; United States. Federal Emergency Relief Administration; West Coast School of Unemployed Workers; Workers' Education Bureau of America; Workers' Education Bureau Press, Inc.
3834441
- Series I. History and Administration
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Audits, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Audits, 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc.
  - Audits, 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Audits, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes correspondence from Matthew Woll, Fifth Vice-President, American Federation of Labor and Peter J. Brady, President, Federation Bank and Trust Company on routine matters (1927); letter from F. P. Keppel, President, Carnegie Corporation, praising the Bureau (1928); financing plan outline from Will McCord, The Organization Finance Bureau.
  - WEB Press Inc. Audits, 1927-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains correspondence from Haley Fiske, President, Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. on routine matters (1929); two letters from Franklin D. Roosevelt, Vice-President, Fidelity and Deposit Trust Company of Maryland praising the objectives of the Bureau (1925) and declining to make a fund raising appeal in the newspapers (1925); correspondence from Dr. Frederick D. Keppel, President, Carnegie Corporation regarding grant application and approval (1932); grant approval notification from W.W. Brierly, Secretary, General Education Board (1934); letter from William Green, President, American Federation of Labor regarding increased contribution (1937); undated loan agreement signed by several members of the Executive Committee of the Bureau.
  - Copyright Registrations, WEB, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes letter from Samuel Gompers, President, American Federation of Labor and correspondence with Florence Thorne, American Federation of Labor on routine matters; suggestions from W. H. Manwaring, The Labor College regarding proposed structure of Bureau courses (5 pp, handwritten).
  - Financial Correspondences, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains correspondence from Florence Thorne, American Federation of Labor regarding articles of agreement between the American Federation of Labor and the Worker's Education Bureau (3 pp typed, 4 handwritten); letter from Matthew Wall, President, International Photo-Engraver's Union regarding the election of executive board chairman; critique of agreement by J. M. Budish, Editor, The Headgear Worker; "American Federation of Labor and Worker's Education", stenographic report of Matthew Woll, Chairman, Education Committee, American Federation of Labor and excerpt of Samuel Gompers's speech delivered at the Second Annual Conference Worker's Education Bureau; letter from Gompers regarding formation of joint executive board; correspondence with Florence Thorne on routine matters; letter from Gompers naming representatives to Executive Committee.
  - Financial Correspondences, 1929-1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes form letter from Matthew Woll urging affiliates to form permanent education committees (2pp, 1924); and routine (1923); routine correspondence with Florence Thorne; proposal to assist in developing labor legislation in Nicaragua from Chester M. Wright, English Language Secretary, Pan American Federation of Labor (1924).
  - General Correspondence, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains correspondence from Florence Thorne regarding labor research and routine matters; Oliver Carlson, Director, Worker's School application for affiliation (and subsequent denial); letter of appreciation from William Green on general labor research; notes and suggestions on a variety of issues connected with the Bureau possibly from Lloyd Cosgrave (12pp handwritten).
  - General Correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes routine correspondence with Florence Thorne; letter of praise to Matthew Woll from Herbert Hoover, Secretary, Department of Commerce.
  - General Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Contains requests of Grace B. Kleug, Chairman, Educational Committee of the Ladies Auxiliary, International Association of Machinists for advice on initiating an education program; routine correspondence from William Green; letter opposing limiting membership of Executive Committee from Fannia Cohn, Executive Secretary, Education Department International Ladies Garment Workers Union; letter praising the commencement of regularly scheduled conferences from William Green.
  - General Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes correspondence from James H. Maurer, Superintendent, Department of Accounts and Finance (Reading, PA) reluctantly agreeing to remain President of the Worker's Education Bureau (1928)
  - General Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes correspondence and attachments with William Green concerning preliminary plan for developing a Department of Education within the American Federation of Labor (1931).
  - General Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Contains queries from the executive officers of the Bureau regarding the continued solvency of the Bureau; correspondence with Frances Perkins, Secretary of Labor regarding establishing an Education Department within the Labor Department; affiliation fee from David Dubinsky, President, International Ladies Garment Worker's Union; letter regarding funds for Bureau run labor institutes from Horse A. Cartwright, Director, American Association for Adult, Education.
  - General Correspondence, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Statement given by Thomas E. Burke, President, Workers Education Bureau, at a conference called by the Secretary of Labor and the Commissioner of Education (1934); correspondence with Peter J. Burke regarding the anticipated affiliation of the Worker's Education Council of New York City (1934); correspondence from William Green regarding the Western Labor College (1935).
  - General Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes routine correspondence from William Green(1939); letter of praise from George Meany, Secretary-Treasurer, American Federation of Labor (1941); four photographs labeled "WEB 20th Anniversary-April 1941".
  - General Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Contains correspondence with Mark Starr, Chairman, Labor Advisory Council, Worker's Service Program, WPA regarding the beginning of the Labor Extension Service under the auspices of the U.S. Department of Labor; letter from C.J. Haggerty, President, California Federation of Labor refusing to participate in programs offered by the People's Educational Center; letter from William Wolff, Executive Secretary, People's Educational Center outlining organization and objective.
  - General Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes letter from Glen Burch, Editor Adult Education Journal regarding postwar activities (1946); correspondence with Florence Thorne, Director of Research, American Federation of Labor regarding suggestions on the Labor Extension Service (1946); routine correspondence with Matthew Woll, Chairman, Committee on Education, American Federation of Labor (1946); routine correspondence from Walter G. O'Donnell, Chairman, Adult Education Committee, American Federation of Teachers, Local 279 (1946).
  - General Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - History Pamphlet, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes plan outline for Organization of Washington Labor Institute from Richard S. Harvey, Lawyer.
  - Positions, 1946-01-1946-05 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Contains several letters from Fannia Cohn in her capacity as a trustee of the Labor Text Book Fund (1922, 1928, 1929).
  - Positions, 1946-06-1946-12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes a refusal to contribute from William L. Hutcheson, General President, United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America (1927); Correspondence with John Brophy regarding his membership on the Executive Board (1927); routine correspondence from James H. Maurer and Thomas E. Burke (1927); letter from William Green regarding the denial of affiliation to the Union Labor College of Pittsburgh (1928), letter from William Collins, General Organizer, American Federation of Labor, regarding John Brophy and the removal of his endorsement by the Pittsburgh Central Labor Union (1928).
  - Positions, 1947-01-1947-03 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    A Brief History of the Origin Development and Present Activities of the National Civic Federation typescript, 22pp.
  - Positions, 1947-05-1947-06 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Routine Correspondence with Harry A. Russell, Regional Director, Worker's Education Bureau (1928, 1929, 1934, 1935); routine correspondence with Nelson Cruikshank of Connecticut (1935); routine correspondence with William Green (1935); letter from Harry A. Russell regarding program implementation (1928).
  - Positions, 1947-07-1947-12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Includes program agenda and selected script for "The People's Platform" which aired weekly from July 20, 1938 to April 23, 1939; program agenda and selected script for "Americans at Work" a program aired weekly from April 28, 1938 to April 15, 1939; correspondence with Sterling Fisher, Director of Education and Radio Talks, Columbia Broadcasting System regarding decision to discontinue research services of the Bureau (1939); routine correspondence front Levering Tyson, Director, National Advisory Council on Radio in Education (1934); letter to Matthew Woll from Franklin D. Roosevelt, Governor, State of New York, praising the radio series (1932); letter from William Green praising radio programs (1932).
- Series II. Organization Activity
  - Correspondence School Institute, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes routine correspondence from Harold Taylor, Chairman, Committee on Ruskin Labor Scholarships (1947).
  - Labor Book Fund, 1921-1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Labor Schools, 1921-1941 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Contains routine correspondence from Matthew Woll, Seventh Vice-president, American Federation of Labor(1923); letter to Lloyd Crosgrave, Assistant Secretary, Worker's Education Bureau regarding the Gary system from F. G. Stecker, Secretary-Treasurer, American Federation of Teachers (1926),
  - National Civic Federation, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New England Division, 1928-1936 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Contains travel authorization for John D. Connors, President, Worker's Education Bureau, to the meeting of the Committee on Education of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
  - Radio Programs, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ruskin College Scholarships, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Ruskin, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes routine correspondence from E. W. Mounce, State Supervisor of Worker's Education Bureau in Missouri (1935); routine correspondence with Paul Vogt, Western Regional Director, Worker's Education Bureau (1935); tentative draft of Worker's Forum from Paul Vogt (1935).
  - Rutgers Institute, 1946-02-1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Rutgers Institute, 1946-07-1946-12 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes correspondence from Chester M. Wright, Editor, International Labor News Service regarding joint venture with the Bureau (1927); criticisms of "Trade Unionism in the Building Industry" from William J. McSorley, President, Building Trades Department, American Federation of Labor and William J. Bowen, President, Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers Union of America (1927); routine correspondence from William Green (1928).
  - Rutgers Institute, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Contains correspondence concerning the litigation Fleming & Reavley vs. The Worker's Education Bureau (1929); Victor C. Olander, Secretary-Treasurer, Illinois Federation of Labor critique of pamphlet (1931).
  - Teacher Training, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Correspondence regarding Samuel Hasanovitch and his unauthorized us of Bureau credentials for the purpose of personal gain.
  - Unemployment, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - UNESCO, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - University Extension, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    "The Pros and Cons of Consumer Credit" by Constance Kent, 16pp. typescript
  - Vocational Education, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    "Labor in the Postwar World" by Dr. John L. Childs, 4pp. reprint
  - Western Division, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    "Labor's Stake Abroad" by Dr. William Withers, 6pp, reprint "Labor and Social Security" by Nelson Cruikshank, 6 pp, photocopied reprint
  - WEB Press, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    "Workers Education: What? Why? How?" by John D. Connors, 18pp (12pp typescript, 6pp photocopy) "Money and How It Works" by Jerry Voorhis, 6 pp, (5pp photocopy, 1p reprint).
  - WEB Press (Box 2, Folder 48)
    "Workers Interdependence in Our Economy" by Arthur A. Elder, 6pp, reprint (plus additional typescript, reprint and photocopies)
  - WEB Press, 1929-1935 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    "Sweden: Laboratory in Economic Democracy" by Arnold S. Zander, 17 pp, typescript (plus additional reprints)
  - WEB Press, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    "Labor and the Law" by Matthew Woll, 6pp, reprint "Organized Labor's Stake in Tax Policy" by Arthur A, Elder, 6pp, reprint.
  - WEB Spring Conference, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    "Labor and UNESCO" by John D. Connors, 6pp, reprint (plus additional reprints) "The Soviet System - of Mind Control" by George S. Counts, 3pp. Reprint
- Series III. Publications and Research
  - Annual Reports, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    "Short Stories on Economics", 12pp. typescript.
  - Article Series, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "More Short Stories on Economics", 12pp. typescript.
  - Pub-Art Series, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    "National Defence", 13 pp, typescript. "More on National Defense", 12pp, typescript,
  - Pub-Art Series, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    "America at War", 13pp, typescript, "The World at War", part I-VI, 13 pp, typescript.
  - Publications-Art. Series, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    "The World at War", part VII-XII, 12pp, typescript. "After the War", 12pp, typescript
  - Publications-Art. Series, 1947-01-1947-06 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Pamphlets
  - Publications-Art. Series, 1947-07-1947-12 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence from William Green regarding opportunity for the American Federation of Labor and the American Library Association to cooperate.
  - Publications-Art. Series, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Publications-Art. Series, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cosgrave Articles, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cosgrave Articles, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cosgrave Articles, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cosgrave Articles, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cosgrave Articles, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Original, manuscript
  - Lecture Series, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Libraries, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publications-Misc., 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Publications-Misc., 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Misc., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Routine correspondence with Dr. Carole Blume, Dr. Mollie Ray Carol/ Director of Research and Ursula Batchelder Stone.
  - Publications-Pam., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Publications-Pam., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pamphlet Series, 1921-1925 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Pamphlet Series, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Contains original typescript and sketches
  - Pamphlet Series, 1934-1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Manuscript
  - Pocket History of AFL-CIO, 1920-1926 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Press Releases, 1935-1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Railway Review, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    11pp, miscellaneous reprints
  - Reading List Series, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Research, 1924-1928 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Research, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Research, 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Research DIV. Pams, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Research Series, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Publications-Shop Stewards Manual Long Sketches, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Shop Steward Manual (Makeup Matrial), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Syllabus Series Pams, 1920-1926 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Syllabus Series Pams, 1935-1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)